<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Self-conviction, or, An enumeration of the absurdities, railings against the college, and physicians in general (but more especially, the writers against the apothecaries), non-sence, irrational conclusions, falsities in matters of fact, and in quotations, concessions, &amp;c. of a nameless person and also, an answer to the rest of Lex talionis / collected and made by Christopher Merrett ...</title>
            <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12411245</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12411245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 284:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Self-conviction, or, An enumeration of the absurdities, railings against the college, and physicians in general (but more especially, the writers against the apothecaries), non-sence, irrational conclusions, falsities in matters of fact, and in quotations, concessions, &amp;c. of a nameless person and also, an answer to the rest of Lex talionis / collected and made by Christopher Merrett ...</title>
                  <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Allestry ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lex talionis.</term>
               <term>Pharmacists --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Great Britain --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61526:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SELF-CONVICTION:</hi> OR AN ENUMERATION OF THE <hi>Abſurdities, Railings,</hi> againſt the <hi>College,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in general; (but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the Writers againſt the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>) Non-ſence, Irrational Concluſions, Falſities in matters of Fact, and in Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Conceſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a nameleſs Perſon.</p>
            <p>AND ALSO An Anſwer to the reſt of <hi>Lex Talionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected and made by <hi>CHRISTOPHER MERRETT,</hi> Dr. in <hi>Phyſic,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Alleſtry,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61526:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61526:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SELF-CONVICTION;</hi> OR AN ENUMERATION OF THE <hi>Abſurdities, Railings</hi> againſt the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TWo days ſince, there came to my hands, a Book entituled, <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> &amp;c. and alſo a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended diſcovery of the frauds of the <hi>Doctors</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, and practiſing Pharmacy. I ſoon ran it over, and found little but railing and non-ſence in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of it, and not one proof made in the later; inquiring into the Author of it, I was informed that the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> gave out, Mr: <hi>Stubbs</hi> was ſo; though common Fame long ſince ſaid, that he intended ſomething to that purpoſe againſt Dr. <hi>Goddard,</hi> and my Self; and though the former report was ſtrong, yet it could never enter into my thoughts, that he had the leaſt finger in a piece ſo illogical, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61526:3"/>
both as to matter and language. I cannot ſay whether the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Company, or any ſingle perſon of them did compoſe it, from whom I might expect an anſwer, which they promiſed at our <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> about a Month ſince; but this I ſhall ſay, that if they are the Authors of it, they have done moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently, in publiſhing a paper at ſuch a time, when they make overtures to the <hi>College.</hi> From the bold daring at Latin and Greek, and miſuſing the <hi>College,</hi> together with the reſt of the Errors recited in my View, <hi>p.</hi> 60. which this nameleſs Writer is guilty of, any one may conjecture rightly of what Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he is. And although this Book appear in the form of a Libel, without name or Licence to it, ſo that in reaſon it concerns me not to take public notice of it at all; but more eſpecially, ſince I could find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, worthy of a reply; yet ſince 'tis the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the ignorant part of the World, to think every Book anſwer'd, if there come forth another with that Title, though it contain nothing at all of that nature, I thought fit to reſolve it into its parts, finding I had little elſe to do, then by collecting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the non-ſence, railing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the only way to reply, hating with all my Soul all perſonal abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and therefore ſhall not take up the common way of retaliation, by reviling again my adverſary, but by ſhewing openly the man in his own words and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ſufficient to convince any one of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs and folly, and ſhall follow the method propoſed in the Title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerve,</hi> That <hi>A.</hi> ſignifies the <hi>Anonymus,</hi> or name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perſon, and <hi>M.</hi> Dr. <hi>Merrett.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin firſt with his revilings againſt the <hi>College.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61526:3"/>Becauſe <hi>A.</hi> every where complains, that the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> out of malice write againſt them, and forſake their Shops; I leave it to the Reader, whether the reaſon given by <hi>M. p.</hi> 32. Where I ſay that the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and daily compariſons and intruſions, daily complained of by my <hi>Collegues,</hi> were a great cauſe of my departing from them; beſides, their railings at the <hi>College</hi> in general, and beſpattering them with notorious untruths; their Cheats (which I often ſay was an ungrateful taſk for me to diſcover) be not cauſe ſufficient for <hi>Phyſicians</hi> to make all their own Medicines; which <hi>A.</hi> hath fully made out in theſe words, <hi>p. 4. A. The Law might as well have ſet 2 Shoe-makers, as Cenſors, to be Judges of the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries Medicines; Thoſe</hi> Cenſors <hi>for the moſt part not underſtanding the tithe of the Medicines and Drugs in the</hi> Apothecaries <hi>Shops: M.</hi> which, leſt his ignorant Reader (to whom he ſaith he writes) ſhould forget, repeats, <hi>p. 8. Moſt of the</hi> Doctors <hi>not underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tithe of what is commonly uſed; M.</hi> and in anſwer to what I object, they bring not their Servants to be examined according to their Charter; <hi>A.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Maſter and Wardens are beſt able to poſe by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and try whether their Servants be well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed or not. M.</hi> Pray <hi>A.</hi> aſk Mr. <hi>Littler,</hi> whether when Warden, 5 of their Servants examined by me together, could anſwer to one Queſtion was aſked them? nay whether they did not all of them commit 6 Errors, in making the moſt vulgar Medicine, the <hi>Lenitive Electuary,</hi> where 'tis enjoyned, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of the ingredients ſhould be made <hi>S. A.</hi> But as to this part, when occaſion ſerves, more ſhall be ſaid and to many other things: and whether alſo the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61526:4"/>
Maſters and Wardens had not approved them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came to this examination. <hi>A. p. 15. There is too much of Self in the College;</hi> p. 20. <hi>nothing muſt be left out of the</hi> Phyſicians <hi>Medicines, though never ſo impertinent, as you may obſerve in their Diſpenſatory corrected by</hi> Culpeper, and he ſaith elſewhere, <hi>witneſs the</hi> Pharmacopaea Lond. <hi>correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by</hi> Culpeper; <hi>the Medicines in the Diſpenſatory (no thanks to them) were in print in ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors long before theirs,</hi> p. 23. <hi>on the Faith of the</hi> College. <hi>(I think that is no better then other mens) and this I know, with others that have tryed when they had formerly a public Laboratory in</hi> Amen Corner, <hi>with Chymiſts of their own providing; there was as baſe Medicines, and Preparations, put off by them, as any other Chymiſts in</hi> London, p. 24. <hi>Here you have the</hi> Colleges <hi>profound propoſals, for an Agreement. M.</hi> This is not ſo, 'tis far below the <hi>College,</hi> (and is no truer then what ſome of them gave out, they were deſired by the <hi>College,</hi> not to give an anſwer to our Books,) to make any propoſals to <hi>Apothecaries. A. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meer</hi> Chimaeras, <hi>and reſolutions to the contrary; and a meer impoſing, not only on the</hi> Apothecary, <hi>but the reſt of the people; therefore moſt abſurd.</hi> Ibid. <hi>After all their propoſed method for agreement, being ſo unreaſonable and baſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> The next thing ſhall be his railings, and odious compariſons. <hi>A. For doubtleſs the diſcreet</hi> Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary <hi>being learned, may make a far abler</hi> Phyſician, <hi>than the</hi> Phyſician <hi>an</hi> Apothecary; <hi>for it is but join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Theory to his Practice, and he may be compleat; but a</hi> Phyſician <hi>cannot ſo eaſily attain to Pharmacy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a myſtery. M.</hi> Which in vulgar acceptation is the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61526:4"/>
knaviſh part of a Trade. <hi>A. For the parts of Phyſic may be attained by the one as well as the other,</hi> p. 9. <hi>'Tis true that ſome</hi> Doctors <hi>Bills could not be made without ſome alteration of the</hi> Apothecary, <hi>the ſame I affirm,</hi> p. 30. <hi>and</hi> p. 11. <hi>Seriouſly, I will ſooner make uſe of an experienced, learned</hi> Apothecary, <hi>then ſome</hi> Phyſicians. Ib. <hi>There is nothing that the greateſt</hi> Arcana-monger <hi>can attain, but the learned and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious</hi> Apothecary <hi>may attain to the ſame or better. When the</hi> Doctors <hi>have taught Ladies, &amp;c. to make Clyſters, they had beſt give them too. (M.</hi> I think <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> themſelves do not give Ladies Clyſters.) <hi>A. The people in</hi> England, <hi>have received as much good by the taking of a penny-worth of Mithridate or Treacle, as others who have given</hi> 10 s. <hi>to a</hi> Doctor <hi>for a Fee. Suppoſeth</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>underſtanding, intelligent perſons, fit for the practice in Phyſic,</hi> p. 16. <hi>A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Chymiſtry will go a great way with them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments. p. 17. I could tell a way to Commence</hi> Doctor, <hi>and eaſier learned then an</hi> Apothecary <hi>will take an Apprentice. M.</hi> Pray <hi>A.</hi> Teach us the way. <hi>A. I believe ſome of them have come in that way, and Equipage. For now there muſt be the little Coach and 2 Horſes, which in theſe days are very uſual appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices to them. So that to ſay a</hi> Doctor <hi>goes to ſee a</hi> Patient, <hi>is too pedantic for our Age, and being thus attended, half a piece for a Fee is but ill taken, and popt perhaps into their left Pocket, and poſſible may cauſe the</hi> Patient <hi>to ſend to his Worſhip (before he will come again) to the hazard of another Angel. M.</hi> To which <hi>A.</hi> adds, <hi>p.</hi> the 3d. <hi>A Velvet Jump, a pair of ſilk Stockings, and a Cane with a ſilver Head,</hi> p. 17. <hi>M.</hi> And from this handſome ſupport of <hi>Phyſicians (A.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61526:5"/>
Pray take heed of that) <hi>A.</hi> Ib. <hi>The Doctors were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo eminent, and encouraged as of late times, there being more Knighted then hath been known in ſo ſhort a time. Their Worſhips Greatneſs,</hi> p. 19. Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries <hi>are as capable of Philoſophy, Arts, Anatomy, and the practic part as themſelves, and many of them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them better then ſome licentiate</hi> Doctors. <hi>M.</hi> A Name often uſed, but never tells what he means by them. <hi>A. Ib. The Ladies having learned to make Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Plaſters, Ointments, Conſerves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(that is, thoſe only they know how to make up) M.</hi> And ſure no <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary</hi> can do more. <hi>A. And by that time</hi> Phyſicians <hi>have taught them to make Clyſters, and Decoctions, they may be as famous as the</hi> Doctors. p. 20. <hi>If the</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors <hi>ſhould ſet upon making their own Medicines, and (which will not ſute with their grandeur) wear blew Aprons. M.</hi> Which the Maſters now ſcorn to do. <hi>A.</hi> Apothecaries <hi>may with much eaſe underſtand, and make themſelves as able</hi> Phyſicians <hi>as any that practiſe.</hi> p. 23. <hi>In acute pains it will be beſt to let the</hi> Doctor <hi>alone, and uſe the next honeſt</hi> Apothecary. <hi>Becauſe we cannot truſt the</hi> Apothecaries <hi>for Chymical remedies, which they may do as well as they can truſt the</hi> Phyſicians. p. 24. <hi>Doubtleſs</hi> Apothecaries <hi>are better acquainted with</hi> Materia medica, <hi>then moſt</hi> Phyſicians, <hi>and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to the Deſcriptions, and Qualities of Plants.</hi> p. 25. <hi>That</hi> Apothecaries <hi>are able to practiſe Phyſic, was proved from the nature of Diſeaſes, and the ſeveral ways they admit of Cure (M.</hi> Make ſence of it if you can) <hi>A. And pray you why may they not be Maſters of this as well as your ſelf, ſome of them?</hi> ib. <hi>Let but a rational, learned</hi> Apothecary (<hi>M.</hi> Titles never gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them by any but by A.) <hi>add but the Theory to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61526:5"/>
his former Obſervations, he may be better fitted for practice, and I will ſooner engage him then many</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians. <hi>An</hi> Apothecary <hi>by induſtry and Obſervation, may be a Maſter of as great</hi> Arcanums, <hi>as any what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever practiſing. The ingenious</hi> Apothecary <hi>being well read in Phyſic,</hi> viz. <hi>in</hi> Frambeſarius, Riverius; <hi>who till of late days was the only approved Author. M.</hi> (Abſurd) for he dy'd not long ſince. <hi>And in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridion medicum, <hi>which coſts but 1s. 6d. may be as fit and capable of the practice of Phyſic, as any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> By all which, he hath manifeſtly proved, and the firſt impudently in print too (much like his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Cocket,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>ſhort View) p.</hi> 24. what I have alledged of their railings, and private back-bitings, to which he anſwereth nothing. But now to my uſe of terror, as he calls it.</p>
            <p>Now this being apparently ſo, what learned and ingenious <hi>Phyſician</hi> can brook ſuch unworthy and unſufferable affronts, as I have elſewhere ſaid? And I leave it to all mens judgments, whether it be not high time for the <hi>College,</hi> and all <hi>Phyſicians</hi> to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their honour, which cannot be done by any other way then what hath been propoſed by my Book; and to wipe off all thoſe imputations of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> and <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> which will neceſſarily follow upon making their own Medicines, and for the which this <hi>A.</hi> hath railed upon me and others my Fellow Writers againſt them, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the next Paragraph. And whether the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> will not be judged by the preſent and after Ages, negligent of their own concerns in not ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And that they do not act the ſame againſt the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61526:6"/>
               <hi>Apothecaries</hi> they heretofore did againſt the <hi>Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons,</hi> for a far leſs crime committed by ſome meaner perſons of that Company, to wit, for ſaying, the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> could only read upon, but not diſſect bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Whereupon the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> excluded them from diſſecting bodies at their <hi>College;</hi> and ſoon taught the World, how well they could work at it. And hence it is, that ſo many worthy diſcoveries have been made by them, ſince they have put their own hands to diſſect. The like advance will happen to the practical part of Phyſic, when <hi>Phyſicians</hi> vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to work upon natural things themſelves, and I am ſure will find both greater ſatisfaction, and alſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by advance their own ſkill and profeſſion, to their full worth and dignity, as well as the publick to greater profit and contentment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A's</hi> Revilings againſt us are, <hi>p. 1. By opprobrious, and unhandſome Billings-gate Language,</hi> p. 2. <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> alias <hi>Railing. He ſhamefully inſinuates ridiculous ſtories. Poſe his Worſhip, Eight-ly, Tenth-ly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This lyes a little too wide. M.</hi> Good Sir, not ſo much as 8000 <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>one year for Fees. A. Frothy Objections, new Whims, and Inventions, Whims and Novelties; Quarrelſome Doctor, Worſhipful Doctor, your. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian and falſe Pamphlet, Cloſet Doctors, his Stories, notorious Falſities, and elſewhere ſordid Allegories,</hi> e. g. <hi>to abuſe</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>a pittiful ſhift, meer</hi> Chimaeras. <hi>Abuſers, and Traducers of the whole Company, Oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious language, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable and baſe deſigns, As en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus as</hi> Diabolus. <hi>Strange uncouth expreſſions, Doctors Calumnies, Frothy Diſcourſe, a Saint Doctor, Diſ-ingenious, and abſurd practice, as ridiculous as the Author; Old quacking ſhifts, gingling diſcourſe, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61526:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a moſt ſevere and uncharitable Cenſure. The Doctor is ſo deficient in Phyſiologie, that he thinks any</hi> Apothecary <hi>honeſt. M.</hi> Underſtand it who can for me. <hi>From a debauched Doctor Apothecary and Chirurgeon,</hi> Libera me Domined <hi>M.</hi> With many more the like.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe he often complains of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I give them; here ſhall follow all I meet with my Book; Illiterate perſons, Unſkillful, every pitiful fellow, pitiful, ignorant, and ſelf-ended Souls. I know no other Epithets I have given them; whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears how juſtly he accuſeth me of malice, revilings, and diſgracing them with truth (as will appear by and by) if by his not anſwering (as every man will think) he confeſſeth, to what <hi>A.</hi> anſwers not.</p>
            <p>Next follow his falſities in matter of Fact, and miſs Quotations. <hi>A. Cuſtos Argentorum, ſucceſsful,</hi> for not unſucceſsful. <hi>Cheats,</hi> for Artifices. <hi>The Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors examiners;</hi> where he leaves out the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> beſides, I am ſure that the Goldſmiths, and Pewterers, have not any ſuperviſors that are not of their own Company. <hi>A. Limons and Citrons,</hi> for Syrup of Limons and Citrons. <hi>A. Inventing matter and deſigns, and diſcover them himſelf, Dr.</hi> M. <hi>a good</hi> Apothecaries Phyſician. Apothecaries <hi>uſed in the ſmall Pox. M.</hi> p. 3. He omits <hi>Privet Beryes,</hi> and there aſks, what is got by ſelling <hi>Dog Beryes,</hi> for <hi>Spina Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina;</hi> ſurely ſomewhat, becauſe the one is found almoſt in every Ditch, the other much more rarely. He miſtakes <hi>Pil. ſtomach. ſec. gen.</hi> in the <hi>London Diſpenſatory,</hi> unleſs <hi>ſec. gen.</hi> in ſome language inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him ſignifies <hi>cum gummi.</hi> He makes a good verſe of <hi>variabimus tela,</hi> for <hi>Artes.</hi> An old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61526:7"/>
               <hi>Garrulus medicus laboranti morbus. M.</hi> This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is not in <hi>Eraſmus Chiliads. A. Sp. of</hi> CC. <hi>cryed up by me, contracting with</hi> Apothecaries <hi>forgot by me;</hi> vid. <hi>View.</hi> p. 18. <hi>A. You promiſed</hi> Chirurgeons <hi>ſhould apply Bliſters and Medicines to the Feet. M.</hi> Where do I ſay ſo? <hi>A. Dr.</hi> M. <hi>not excuſed from filling Cupboards with many Medicines,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>One of your ſelves, Dr.</hi> Goddard <hi>with his Drops. M.</hi> Whom you might have diſtinguiſhed from my learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Collegue, Dr. <hi>Jonathan Goddard,</hi> had you not a mind to have aſperſt him, as well as elſewhere you do the Judicious Dr. <hi>Thomas Cox,</hi> from Dr. <hi>Daniel Cox,</hi> whom you there groſly miſtake; for I aſſure you, he is not ſo good a Friend to your ways as you imagine, but the other <hi>Goddard</hi> was none of our ſelves. <hi>Apothecaries</hi> may be the verieſt Knaves, he omits <hi>without diſcovery.</hi> In one place I complain of ſtrong Pills given, he leaves out ſtrong, though little to his advantage, and makes no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a Vomit, and Pills. I ſay <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in the late Wars, kept up, as to learning, the honour of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>A.</hi> replyes, <hi>The</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>p. 17. out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did them in ſupplyes, when the Exigence of affairs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. M.</hi> And to mention but one more amongſt multitudes (which I am neceſſitated to omit) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I deſign to be brief, <hi>viz.</hi> when he often calls us Aggreſſors; But that <hi>Apothecaries</hi> have been the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors firſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> by uſurping our profeſſion (which he himſelf confeſſeth) they have done for a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years laſt paſt, without being ever queſtioned for it, as I have ſaid elſewhere; beſides, their revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of us, as hath been proved, but if our diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in print of the former, and alſo of their Cheats,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61526:7"/>
which I can prove have been as ancient as their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; then I muſt confeſs we are the Aggreſſors, which I think no ingenious perſon will judg, but lay that accuſation upon themſelves, becauſe of their firſt aſſaulting us in our imployments and Credits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nonſence.</hi> Some whereof happily may be for his want of Grammar (I cannot better excuſe him) which he hath ſufficiently ſhewed in falſe improper Greek, and Latin, which he uſeth, though but little, and whereby he muſt needs ſhew himſelf an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary,</hi> ſuch a one as I have deſcribed in my <hi>View. A. Dr.</hi> M. <hi>and Dr.</hi> Cox, <hi>contradict themſelves, as they have done in all Ages. The old Medicines are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more ſafe then his new Inventions, as</hi> Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates <hi>affirms.</hi> Treacle-water <hi>ſo much magnified by fire. Authentic Medicines. Medicines the</hi> Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>ſupport and notions. For a</hi> Phyſician <hi>to give his Medicines</hi> gratis, <hi>is enough to diſcourage any ingenious perſon to follow it. M.</hi> And to ſay no more, but what every Reader may obſerve in many places, that they are unintelligible.</p>
            <p>Next follow his Conceſſions of what I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged againſt them. <hi>A. As the failings of ſome few. He might have paſſed over other</hi> Apothecaries <hi>failings. Theſe diſcoveries might have unadviſedly ſlipt from the</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>or their Servants;</hi> Nemo omnibus horis ſapit. <hi>M.</hi> But doubtleſs they will be cloſer hereafter. <hi>A. He acknowledgeth good</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries Phyſicians. <hi>Dr.</hi> Goddard (<hi>M.</hi> He means him with the Drops) <hi>Had the knack as well as the</hi> Apothecaries. <hi>Queſtionleſs theſe miſtakes are rare. The Cloſet</hi> Doctors <hi>may be miſtaken as well as the</hi> Apothecaries. <hi>A little ordinary practice among ſome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61526:8"/>
of them. Good reaſon</hi> Apothecaries <hi>ſhould cry up their good</hi> Phyſicians. <hi>He teacheth the Company better manners in his own words, when they come next to dine at their Hall; if the</hi> Apothecary <hi>had made a</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians <hi>Bill, the</hi> Patient <hi>would have been truly his</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. He confeſſeth alſo, <hi>that Noſtrums do undo them. M.</hi> As for his Logic, eſpecially in that part wherein he promiſeth to diſcover the Frauds, and Abuſes, committed by <hi>Doctors</hi> profeſſing, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing <hi>Pharmacy;</hi> he argues all along. <hi>A. They may be Cheats,</hi> ergo <hi>they are; and therefore perſwades him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that Dr.</hi> M. <hi>who hath diſcovered ſo many Cheats and falſities doth practiſe them. M.</hi> I ſay <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> were <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Servants; <hi>A.</hi> infers, that I ſay, the whole Company is ſo; now he there ſaith, <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> have no dependance on <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> 'tis true of practiſing <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> but to ſay others have not, is nonſence; and through all his Book, he thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. <hi>A. Poſſibly, Doubtleſs, Queſtionleſs, Perhaps, Likely, I ſuppoſe, I hear, it is more then probable, it may be, 'tis feared, I believe, without doubt, or I do not believe; much may be ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>M.</hi> And this is all the proofs he hath in what he aſſerts, you ſhall ſcarcely find a page in his Book, where this reaſoning is not, I am ſure in moſt pages ſeveral times. 'Tis moſt certain, that he hath not given one inſtance to prove any Frauds in <hi>Phyſicians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> according to his Title Page, more then ſhewing a poſſibility, that it may be ſo. He rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons here as well as he doth all along, that <hi>Apothecaries</hi> may be learned and able in Phyſic; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are ſo. And that <hi>Phyſicians</hi> will never Cheat, I think I have given a ſolid reaſon elſewhere, that ſo to do is to his diſadvantage. And for the ſame reaſon, I cannot but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61526:8"/>
think, that the practiſing <hi>Apothecaries</hi> who ſold <hi>Myrtle leaves</hi> for <hi>Sena,</hi> &amp;c. to thoſe they call their own <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> did give good <hi>Sena,</hi> but to the <hi>Doctors Patients, Myrtle leaves.</hi> And here I might conclude, this pitiful Writer having ſufficiently confuted himſelf: But I ſhall briefly run over what he objects more in his Book; adding by the by, what he omits to anſwer. In the head of Cheats, he anſwers to the firſt, that other men may be Knaves as well as <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> he anſwers nothing to Cheat, the <hi>2d. 3d. 4th. 5th. 6th. 7th. 8th. 9th.</hi> and <hi>10th.</hi> to the complaints of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying Bills, nothing to the firſt, <hi>2d. 3d. 4th. 5th. 6th. 7th. 8th.</hi> and acknowledgeth the <hi>9th.</hi> of the good <hi>Apothecaries Phyſician,</hi> that in ſetting down in their Bills <hi>Pearl,</hi> and <hi>Bezoar,</hi> he anſwereth, that ſome <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have plyed their <hi>Patient</hi> with <hi>Sp. CC. Elixir Proprietatis.</hi> Whereof I think no man can give one <hi>Patient</hi> half an Ounce in a weeks time, which at his rate will coſt but <hi>2s. 6d.</hi> though a Chymiſt told me they would give him but <hi>1s. 6d.</hi> an ounce, when they have run upon his Book, <hi>p. 5th. p. 6th. A.</hi> ſaith, <hi>This lyeth a little too wide, to make Cuſtomers pay 11, or 12 ſhillings for a pint of Juleb. M.</hi> For once let it be but <hi>10s.</hi> but he tells me I have left out the main ingredient, which cauſeth the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Bill to be ſharp. One whereof he ſaith, <hi>is the</hi> Apothecaries <hi>freedom in lending the young</hi> Phyſician <hi>a room and Servants to attend him, and the Miſtreſs too,</hi> Urgente neceſſitate, <hi>P O for that. M.</hi> This I underſtand not, I hope he means no hurt to the Huſband, however 'tis unjuſt the <hi>Patient</hi> ſhould pay for the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> freeneſs to the <hi>Phyſician.</hi> The ſecond reaſon, as he ſaith, is forgot by me. <hi>M.</hi> 'Tis
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61526:9"/>
given in my <hi>18th.</hi> page. As to their affronts to the <hi>College, pag.</hi> 21. 22. 23. 24. he only barely ſaith, <hi>A. They would have introduced an unlimited power, which the wiſdom of our Nation thought very unequal, and would not allow.</hi> M. 'Tis more then you know, for the Committee, as I ſaid, never gave a report of that buſineſs to the Parliament. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>A.</hi> ſaith, <hi>I call them ſawcy for calling the ſick their</hi> Patients. <hi>M.</hi> But I demonſtrated it to be non-ſence, which is not ſo of the Attorney and his Clyent, which are as truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives, as <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Patient. p.</hi> 8. <hi>A.</hi> ſaith, <hi>I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not any eminent Practitioners in</hi> London, <hi>in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times have made their own Medicines. M.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not, becauſe <hi>Apothecaries</hi> then uſed none of thoſe miſchiefs complained of in my Book, and therefore the <hi>Phyſician</hi> need not then put himſelf to that trouble and charge as now he doth. As to the benefits ariſing by practiſing <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> he ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all in <hi>page</hi> 28. 29. nor any thing of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the inconveniencies of ſending Bills to them, <hi>p.</hi> 29. 30. to <hi>page</hi> 34. where he ſaith, <hi>A. The giving of Medicines by the</hi> Phyſicians gratis; <hi>This is a wiſe knack of a Doctor, juſt as broad as long; if you will pay for the Gooſe, he will give you the ſauce. M.</hi> Nay, there is a great difference; for grant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to be the Gooſe, and the Medicines the Sauce; and ſuppoſe the <hi>Patient,</hi> or buyer, will give 5s. for the Gooſe (for every one giveth the <hi>Phyſician</hi> as he pleaſeth and is able) the Knaviſh Cook, to follow his ſimile, which in the Caſe propoſed is the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary,</hi> may make him pay as he liſt, even to <hi>40s;</hi> now without doubt, every man will rather pay <hi>5s.</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for both, then dividedly trebble his charge.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61526:9"/>
               <hi>p.</hi> 17. He ſtands up for the old Medicines, whereof in <hi>page</hi> 31. <hi>A.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The</hi> Apothecary <hi>need not be troubled, to his great charge in making, and having in readineſs, ſo many unprofitable and uncouth Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. M.</hi> So that he hath here anſwered that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection for me. Yet I will add to that, one more of my own, <hi>i. e.</hi> if the <hi>Opium</hi> were left out of thoſe greater Compoſitions, I think no <hi>Apothecary</hi> would give <hi>4d.</hi> a pound for it, for any uſe, unleſs it were to put <hi>Opium</hi> to it, and make it up again; and I have to ſome <hi>Phyſicians</hi> merrily compared <hi>Mathew</hi>'s Pill to thoſe great Medicines, who have given the preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to the later. Beſides, I never ſaid they were bad Medicines, but that better, and at ſmaller char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, might be made. But I will ſay no more of thoſe great Idols of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and other igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons that know not, nor ever conſider` the reaſon and nature of Medicines, <hi>p.</hi> 12. As for my Objection againſt the ſo common uſe of Sugar, in Syrups, Conſerves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may not the ſame be confronted by his <hi>page</hi> 31. where he deſires, <hi>that a new</hi> Pharmacopaea Lond. <hi>may be ſet forth, wherein may be ſpared of the Medicines in the old. M.</hi> I doubt not but when that reformation he deſireth cometh, that theſe Conſerves, Syrups, Lohocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and moſt of the diſtilled waters, which make up the bulk of the Shop, will be the: he deſires to be ſpared; and by this your propoſal, what pitiful empty Shops will you have? in the ſame place you would have an addition of ſome other laudable Medicines, which you need not doubt will be ſome of thoſe you call the Whims and Novelties of the Cloſet <hi>Doctors.</hi> In the ſame page you direct alſo, that Medicines may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61526:10"/>
be contracted, but for ſo doing you rail at me in your 20 <hi>page. p.</hi> 15. <hi>A.</hi> makes no difference at all in <hi>Sena,</hi> but puts the uncertainty of working only to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom 'tis adminiſtred, for which he quotes <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> in his falſe Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ibid.</hi> he calls <hi>filii Artis,</hi> a new Sect; which he prophecies, may be as bad or worſe then the <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> but for that we may take his advice, given <hi>p.</hi> 13. where he adviſeth us to keep them to our ſelves, as he ſaith, 'tis beſt ſo to do. <hi>p.</hi> 16. You ſay I cajole the <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> and put the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> and them together by the Ears; Why then you reſolve to fly in the faces of the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons,</hi> for acting but what they ought; for to be ſure they will not quarrel with them. <hi>p.</hi> 18. Whereas you ſay, <hi>In the Plague time, the</hi> Doctors <hi>with their Worſhips greatneſs fled. M.</hi> I anſwer, that few <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> that were able to maintain themſelves abroad, ſtayed in <hi>London.</hi> Neither did any <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> leave the City till the <hi>College</hi> had made choice of as many of themſelves, as the City thought meet to attend that ſervice. Beſides, many Seniors of our <hi>College</hi> remained, as many I dare ſay, as there did of the better ſort of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in proportion, and doubtleſs, 'twas as acceptable ſervice to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>London</hi> (whom he here Claws) to have City <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in the Country with them, where they might have ſome employment alſo; as to ſtay in the City to the hazard of their lives, when they had ſcarce any <hi>Patient</hi> that remained there. <hi>p.</hi> 18. He acknowlegeth all I ſaid, from <hi>p.</hi> 51. to the latter end of 59. <hi>viz.</hi> my digreſſion againſt the Common <hi>Mountebanks</hi> to be true; and ſurely, there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but all indifferent perſons ſhould think, both my
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61526:10"/>
detections to be as ſound and ſolid in all the reſt, as <hi>A.</hi> doth this, <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>A.</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>That Chimiſtry is part of the</hi> Apothecaries <hi>Trade, and denies not but they will fall upon the Trade of Druggiſts, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillers alſo, p.</hi> 21. <hi>M.</hi> He ſeems to anſwer to anſwer my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which he calls my greateſt, becauſe he ſaith nothing to any of the reſt) drawn from the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful encroachment of one Trade upon another. His anſwer is nothing to the purpoſe; for ſaith <hi>A. One that hath a good opinion may make uſe of an</hi> Apothecary. <hi>M.</hi> 'Tis true he may, and offends not the Law but himſelf; But how doth this juſtifie the <hi>Apothecary</hi> that practiſeth on him; and can anothers miſtake diſanul the Law, forbidding <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> &amp;c. to practiſe? And by this reaſoning of his, any man may be a Divine, Lawyer, Chirurgeon, Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (I doubt his Company will not thank him for it) nay any man may ſet up any Trade in <hi>London</hi> (he ſaith, <hi>ſomewhere I may do ſo</hi>) by this Logic, if he can but get Cuſtomers. He goes on and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to what I allege, that the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> practiſe againſt Law. <hi>A.</hi> Anſwers, <hi>Any one may apply out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward applications, and inward Medicines, by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute</hi> (I'le tell him) 'tis that of 34 <hi>H.</hi> 8. and withal ſeveral Pleas made by <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> who were all overthrown upon it. Beſides, ſome of the Judges were of opinion that this was repealed by 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> vid. <hi>Butlers</hi> Caſe in <hi>Crokes</hi> Report, <hi>part</hi> 1. you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this with your good Latin, ſomewhat better then your <hi>Magna in parvâ,</hi> and call it a Maxim in Law; <hi>Quod quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> norit, in eodem exerceat.</hi> This Maxime is againſt all reaſon, and therefore Law in your ſence. I never heard of it, ſurely you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61526:11"/>
ſtake it for that common Maxime of theirs; <hi>Quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ſua Arte credendus,</hi> or <hi>in ſua Arte peritus.</hi> The former is a practical conſequence from the later, and that is a ſuppoſition needful in our Law.</p>
            <p>To the reſt of the Book and Poſtſcript, he ſaith nothing, but only of the relation I had from a Clergy Man, who names no perſon; but <hi>A.</hi> hath made his name out of the letter thus, the ſilly <hi>Apothecary</hi> knows no more then to write to a whole-ſale <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary</hi> in your City, out of which he hath Chriſtned <hi>Wright</hi> the <hi>Apothecary.</hi> I ſay of my Friend, he is well known in Phyſic, whence he infers he is a practiſer too, and then quotes againſt his practice the decrees of the Church, and Dr. <hi>Primroſe,</hi> and then tells you this ſtory might have been better concealed for the honour of the Divines profeſſion (juſt as much as it was againſt Phyſiology before for me to do the like) it being contrary to the rule of Charity, and his great Maſter, to divulge his Brethrens faults, how then ſhall a Divine preach? you would like him well enough, if he had ſpoke, though untruths againſt the <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> and though you in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces revile me for detecting your Cheats, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them; yet you muſt be prais'd for your <hi>Lex Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lionis,</hi> a meer Libel; <hi>A. And in truth there is as much reaſon for</hi> Apothecaries <hi>to change profeſſions and preach, as they to practiſe Phyſic, though I am for neither; M.</hi> (but by his Logic, if they will practiſe Phyſic, he will preach) <hi>A.</hi> This obſerve, <hi>You ſhall ſeldom read or hear of any miſchiefs or abuſes, ſuch as theſe are put in print by the Doctors, but the Parſon muſt have a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the Pye, witneſs in late times,</hi> In Nomine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61526:11"/>And thus Reader, you have ſeen how he hath abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>Divines,</hi> and this makes it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that if a Lawyer ſhould tell him how groſly he miſtakes in <hi>page</hi> 21. the application of the Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, how he would deal with him.</p>
            <p>And now to confirm what I have ſaid throughout, I deſire the Reader to peruſe the <hi>2d.</hi> part of the uſefulneſs of <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> Written by the Honourable Mr. <hi>Boyl,</hi> a Perſon who ſpends both time and purſe for the advancement of all publick good, without intereſt or paſſion; and you will find him there, not only affirm, but prove a good part of what I have ſaid; with ſome quick and ſharp glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> that do not improve Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. I ſhall mention but two, <hi>page</hi> 142. he ſaith of the inventors of <hi>Mithridate,</hi> and <hi>Treacle, A wiſe Man might uſe a remedy which ſcarce any but a Fool would have invented.</hi> Add hereto, what the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zwelfer,</hi> the firſt <hi>Phyſician</hi> that ever went about to reform <hi>Diſpenſatories</hi> (too hard a taſk for <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries.</hi>) All others being either tranſcribers only, or a little alterers of the Shop Medicines ſaith of <hi>Treacle,</hi> and <hi>Mithridate, p.</hi> 428. What was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and premiſed of <hi>Theriaca Andromachi,</hi> may be deſervedly ſaid of <hi>Mithridate,</hi> both as well to the Compoſition its ſelf, as to the rule of preparing it; and a little after, I may rather laugh at, then exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſome of the ingredients; and no leſs worthy of laughter then examination, are there many other ingredients in this pompous Compoſition. Which paſſage is much more ſevere then what I ſaid of them in my <hi>View, p.</hi> 38. where I ſay briefly, that they conſiſt of confuſed and contrary ingredients,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61526:12"/>
and that they are unintelligible and unreaſonable Compoſitions. By this paſſage out of a perſon whoſe Book all <hi>Phyſicians</hi> highly honour, beſides what I allege in the ſame place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how falſly this ignorant <hi>A.</hi> ſpeaks (for you are to believe ſaith he, <hi>this infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Doctors, ipſe dixit) <hi>and that 'tis but one</hi> Doctors <hi>opinion;</hi> and is as true, as he twice affirms, theſe Compoſitions were commended by me to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe my name was to the <hi>Diſpenſatory.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my name is fixed to it, but as Candidate only, not as Fellow; and therefore I had no hand in that Book, and had I been then Fellow of the <hi>College,</hi> I ſhould have given my ſuffrage and approbation to it, notwithſtanding any thing I ſay in my <hi>View,</hi> 20 years after the publication of that <hi>Pharmacopaea.</hi> And again Mr. <hi>Boyl</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 138. '<hi>Tis certain</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Bills of</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>eſpecially in Chronical Caſes, do often prove ſo chargable, that even when the remedies ſucceed, by that time a poor</hi> Patient <hi>is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, he is undone, and pays for the prolongation of his life, that which ſhould have been his livelyhood.</hi> Now Sir, if you pleaſe to add this or any other of his Books to your Library, you may find more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in a few pages of his, then in the whole Library you have commended, and <hi>Certe,</hi> in your own word, you will not judg this Noble Perſon to have written (as you ſay of us) out of malice, or deſign, nor railingly, though more ſharply then our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto the opinion and practice of that Pious and Learned Divine Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> well known for his life and works, who not long<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſince told me, in the preſence of one of my <hi>Collegues,</hi> and an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary,</hi> and ſeveral other perſons of quality, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61526:12"/>
when he practiſed Phyſic in <hi>Kiderminſter</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is rationally ſkilled) he durſt never truſt an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> but practiſed all his own Medicines; and when he gave over, he introduced another into his practice, on this condition only, that he ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe his own remedies.</p>
            <p>And ſo having ſpent a few idle hours, in reading and animadverting on your frivolous papers, I hope you and ſuch as you will leave your railing, and follow your practice, which I did neither in my former Book, nor in this Pamphlet reſtrain you from, or ſet any Conditions, Articles, or Limitations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, according to all your deſires, as your other Antagoniſts do, and therefore have reaſon to expect, you will without murmuring, and tricks, let the Cloſet <hi>Doctors</hi> peaceably enjoy their practice, and then let's try whether you, or ſuch as you, are the abler and honeſter <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> and leave the World to judg, whether our Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are not more ſafe, more pleaſant, more du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and of greater efficacy, and leſs charge by far, and leſs fulſom, then yours of the Shops, and by this means we ſhall all be Friends.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:61526:13"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>COnſidering Reader, This Pamphlet ſhould have come abroad 12 days ſooner, but for ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments, and delays it met with, being all that time out of my hands; Now in this interval, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing again the <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> I thought fit to add ſomewhat in relation to what it allegeth againſt <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> in general, and alſo againſt the blew Apron, or <hi>Cloſet Doctor Apothecaries</hi> (as <hi>A.</hi> calls them) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitting wholy ſome paſſages omitted in each head, and clear inferences eaſily deducible from each of them, enough having been quoted to ſatisfie any indifferent perſon; But before I proceed, I ſhall only take notice of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuity of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi> who before all intelligent men, diſclaim that Book, ſaying the ſame I have ſaid of it, but telling unconſidering, and ignorant perſons, that our Books are fully anſwered; ſo ready are they by double dealing to ſupport their cauſe, ſince no other way can do it.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing <hi>A.</hi> allegeth againſt <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in general, is, in his Preface in theſe words. <hi>They abuſe the</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>perſwading away, and taking from them their friends, and acquaintance, imploying, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61526:13"/>
ſending their Bills, contrary to civility, and Equity, to whom they pleaſe, to the great prejudice of moſt of them, and therefore you will never blame ſome of them, for practiſing, being neceſſitated thereunto for a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood.</hi> p. 14. <hi>the</hi> Doctors <hi>began firſt with the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, <hi>by invading his intereſt, and cauſing ſome of them to practiſe out of neceſſity,</hi> pag. 29. <hi>for it can be nothing leſs then incivility, to make a Gentleman, or other to forſake his friend, by imploying whom he pleaſeth as his</hi> Apothecary, <hi>and this is their common practice. M.</hi> An Example thereof, he there gives of a <hi>Saint Doctor. ib.</hi> p. 29. <hi>A. Another humour of the</hi> Doctor, <hi>which will neceſſitate the</hi> Apothecary <hi>to practiſe, is this, by having a prejudice againſt him (and this is common) ſo that they will not ſuffer his acquaintance to make uſe of him, nor ſend their Bills to him (though this be very diſ-ingenuous and abſurd) but to another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Apothecary. <hi>M.</hi> And then another ſtory of a practiſing <hi>Apothecary,</hi> and after that thus concludes. <hi>A. Here are two ſuch plain Caſes, and ſo common, that unleſs the</hi> Doctors <hi>on their parts will engage, not to deal ſo diſ-ingenuouſly againſt all Equity and Reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the</hi> Apothecary <hi>can have no aſſurance of a ſubſiſtence by his profeſſion, but in practiſing of Phyſic, and p.</hi> 31. <hi>A.</hi> propoſeth, <hi>That if a</hi> Patient <hi>ſendeth for a</hi> Phyſician, <hi>he may make uſe of what</hi> Apothecary <hi>he pleaſeth, for to make up, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter thoſe things preſcribed, nothing more reaſonable, though nothing leſs practiſed,</hi> p. 32. <hi>A.</hi> aſketh, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the common practice of</hi> Phyſicians (<hi>moſt of them having a particular</hi> Apothecary) <hi>to whom uſually they ſend their Bills (though contrary to the</hi> Patients <hi>deſire) and I know what they uſually ſay as to the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61526:14"/>
of it, if this hath not been the very cauſe of the neceſſitating the</hi> Apothecary <hi>to practiſe Phyſic for his neceſſary ſupport. M.</hi> And for this reaſon in ſeveral places, he maketh the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> the Aggreſſors in this quarrel.</p>
            <p>To anſwer and prevent which Objections, I have ſaid ſomewhat in my <hi>View,</hi> p. 46. and I doubt not but the Reader would have been ſatisfied, if <hi>A.</hi> had been pleaſed to have publiſhed the reaſons, he ſaith, he knoweth <hi>Phyſicians</hi> allege for juſtifying their ſo doing, ſome whereof I ſhall here recite. One is a juſt <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> which <hi>A.</hi> by his Title approves of, which ſure he likes as equal and juſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that I ſay in my View, that they commonly ſhuffle out thoſe <hi>Phyſicians</hi> that write only for the <hi>Patients</hi> good, to bring in their good <hi>Apothecaries Phyſician,</hi> to the manifold greater charge of the <hi>Patient,</hi> and nothing more ordinary then for them to brag of this.</p>
            <p>Secondly, All thoſe diſcoveries made in their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting, detracting, falſifying, uſing of unſound Druggs, their tricks of raiſing Bills, and moſt of the advantages I have mentioned, both to <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Patient,</hi> being well reflected on (where I ſhew the advantages both <hi>Patient</hi> and <hi>Phyſician</hi> have in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their own Medicines, not needful here to be recited) will moſt clearly prove ſo many ſolid rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if not a neceſſity of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> carrying away their <hi>Patients</hi> (as they call them) to an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> whoſe honeſty they know both for the true making, and prizing the Medicines, and over whom they have ſome power in thoſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Phyſicians</hi> do it for their own reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For the errors, and deceits of the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61526:14"/>
always reflect on them, as well as the life and health of the <hi>Patients</hi> are concerned thereby.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, 'Tis granted by all, that the <hi>Patient</hi> is wholy ignorant of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Medicines, and practices, which the <hi>Phyſician</hi> doth, or cannot but better know either upon his own experience, or by information of ſome others that know them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this or that <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Medicines be good, or honeſtly made, and therefore hath more reaſon to truſt his reputation, and his <hi>Patients</hi> life with one he knoweth, then with one he knows not, nor hath ever heard of, and for ſecuring both, no <hi>Patient</hi> will but thank him for it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, When an <hi>Apothecary</hi> hath practiſed of his own head, and the <hi>Phyſician</hi> is not called in till ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of danger, what reaſon is there, that he ſhould take upon him the diſcredit of the <hi>Patients</hi> Death (if paſt Cure) or why ſhould he teach that <hi>Apothecary</hi> to practiſe further by curing of him? And thus much and no more of the Equity, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of carrying away <hi>Patients</hi> from <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> though moſt of the pages in my <hi>View,</hi> may ſupply intelligent Readers with reaſons why <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſhould commonly deal thus with them; and this I will here ſay, I never did ſo without ſound reaſon, and to the good content of the <hi>Patient,</hi> accounting in this Caſe the ſucceſs wholy to depend upon my ſelf, being bound in all reaſon to make good the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and ſkill of the commended <hi>Apothecary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next railing expreſſion is, <hi>A. That 'tis inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility ſo to do.</hi> To this I anſwer, that Civility comes from <hi>Civis</hi> a Citizen (as no man that underſtandeth Latin doubts it doth) and conſequently, if Civility
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61526:15"/>
ſignifieth the practice of Citizens (as it doth as cleerly as the other) for Civility comes from <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilis,</hi> which ſignifieth no more then the City uſage; then 'tis moſt plain, that this practice of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> is moſt Civil: for I appeal to each ſingle Citizen, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he thinks it not fair, and equal, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his acquaintance in way of trading to other men of the ſame Trade his known Friends, then which I think there is nothing more commonly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the City. And therefore for ſo doing, he doth tax all the Citizens of incivility, abſurdity, and diſ-ingenuity, for which I preſume they will thank him as much, in <hi>p.</hi> 20. where <hi>A.</hi> ſaith, Phyſicians <hi>may ſell</hi> Grocers <hi>Wares, as well as make Medicines, if they pleaſe.</hi> Neither have I heard any complaint made by any <hi>Apothecary,</hi> when a friend hath carried them from one to another; beſides, why is it not uncivil for one <hi>Apothecary</hi> to carry away anothers Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer?</p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall ſpeak to is, his great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt <hi>Phyſicians</hi> making their own Medicines, <hi>p. 1. A.</hi> ſaith, <hi>That few wiſe men think this is for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, and honour of the profeſſion, and</hi> ibid. <hi>This is the only way in the World to break</hi> Apothecaries. <hi>p. 2. There's knavery in all Trades, the</hi> Phyſicians <hi>not excepted, p. 10. The very naming of</hi> Phyſicians <hi>giving Medicines</hi> gratis, <hi>is enough to diſcourage any ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon to follow it.</hi> ibid. <hi>New inventions and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments are dangerous. p. 13. New Models, new vampt meerly out of deſign, and in ſeveral places whimſyes, p. 31. he propoſeth ſomewhat as to the avoiding thoſe many prejudices, as may ariſe by new inventions (as to the ſanative part) not manifeſt. M.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61526:15"/>
As to this Objection, I anſwer briefly, that having declared at large the great improvements may be, and are made in Phyſic, and that ſuch improvement is, and hath been made, to the great help, comfort, and content of <hi>Patients,</hi> as experience hath taught them; if <hi>A.</hi> had had any prudence or well meaning to the publick good, he would not condemn thoſe things others have found good by, and which he wholy is ignorant of; which no civil or modeſt man will do, though in the ſame place he deſireth an addition and publication of ſuch laudable preparations, as ſhall be judged fit and ſuit the <hi>Therapeutic,</hi> according to the cauſes of Diſeaſes, now of late more perfectly known. Where he acknowledgeth that the old preparations of the Shops, do not (at leaſt) ſo well ſuit the <hi>Therapeutic,</hi> and that ſome preparations may be fitted that will, or elſe why doth he deſire an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſuch? Now I am to tell him, that ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines the <hi>Cloſet Doctors</hi> make. But the great cry of this <hi>A.</hi> and his Brethren is, becauſe we will not (as he ſaith) <hi>ſet them forth and make them manifeſt, viz.</hi> to every <hi>Apothecary</hi> and his Servant to practiſe by, and then to vilifie and abuſe the Inventors, and Founders of them, eſpecially when they are made Maſters of thoſe things, which are better kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, to the Honour and livelyhood of the Inventor, and good opinion of the taker; for ſince ſo it is, that the beſt Medicine poſſibly can be made, muſt neceſſarily ſometimes prove unſucceſsful, if it come once into a Shop, and be made common, it loſeth its value, and eſteem it had whilſt it was in private hands, to the great diſadvantage of the <hi>Patient,</hi> and hence it is that <hi>Apothecaries</hi> making uſe of ſome
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61526:16"/>
private receipt of a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> frequently gets more money by concealing it as his own, then the Inventor ever did. And this private way of getting receipts from <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> is the principal, if not the ſole cauſe of ſetting up <hi>Mountebanks</hi> in the World. But becauſe examples prove more with the vulgar then reaſon doth, I ſhall conclude this Objection by an inſtance in a Perſon much commended in ſeveral places by this <hi>A. viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> (who was the great Practitioner I mentioned in my <hi>View,</hi> of whom an <hi>Apothecary</hi> ſaid, that his Boy could write as good a Bill as he (ſome of whoſe Books you to no purpoſe quote in <hi>p.</hi> 26. 27.) hath gained that great opinion in the World by concealed Medicines made by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and prudently diſtributed in his own practice, and to his own <hi>Apothecary</hi> only, or by himſelf; and ſurely, if this <hi>A.</hi> had any thing to do in the World, he muſt take notice of it. Two of which, <hi>viz.</hi> his preparation of Steel, and Brimſtone, he mentioneth not in one place only, are not unknown to ſome of the <hi>Cloſet Doctors,</hi> as well as many other ſecrets, of as good if not better effects as they, ſuch are thoſe you call whimſies uſed by thoſe that detect your Cheats. 'Tis certain you commend not this practice in the learned Dr. <hi>Willis.</hi> Sure I am, an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary</hi> told me he had ſeen a preparation of Steel, for the receipt whereof he would have given an 100 <hi>l.</hi> but being ſhewed by a <hi>Cloſet Doctor,</hi> ſuch a preparation which he preferred before that other, no more words were made of it. Such are the whimſies, and novelties, invented by ſuch you ſo much rail at in your own defence, being able to do no otherwiſe. And having thus a ſecond time abſolved my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61526:16"/>
in the performance of my double promiſe (equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to an Oath) to proſecute by all lawful ways, illiterate <hi>Empirics.</hi> I now now reſolve to ſit quiet, and leave any further defence to ſuch, whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns perhaps more then my ſelf, and the reſt, who by making their own Medicines, and by their Pens endeavour the publick good, and the honour of their profeſſion, ſlighting the malitious forgeries, and tricks contrived againſt us. I ſay the vindication from the ſlanders mentioned in <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> (the common language of moſt <hi>Apothecaries</hi>) reflects wholy on ſuch as make not their own Medicines. For ſuch as do, muſt be knowing in Drugs, and Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; muſt know the whole proceſs of preparing, and ordering them into Medicines, which they are willing to demonſtrate (there being no other way) to any perſon whatſoever. And do hereby offer (without the leaſt vain-glory) to accept any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal to be made by the Company of the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> whereby they may clear to the World by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual operation and viſible demonſtration, how far ſome of the <hi>Cloſet Doctors</hi> ſurpaſs them, both in the knowledge of all natural things, and in well order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them for Medicines, together with the <hi>ratio componendi.</hi> And all this upon whatſoever conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> ſhall think fit to propoſe. Which if they do not (as I am ſure they will not, though many advantages ſhall be allowed them) then let all the World judg, how falſly and undeſervingly they ſlander us, and as they have done my ſelf in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial; And we doubt not to prove them in the whole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Empirics,</hi> in their own Trade, as I have ſaid in my <hi>View.</hi> And now I muſt beg pardon of all Learned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61526:17"/>
men, eſpecially thoſe of my own Art, that I have deſcended ſo low, as to cope with ſuch unworthy Adverſaries; hoping the zeal for our profeſſion, will plead my excuſe; and for this my expectation, the Tongues and Pens of many give me full aſſurance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61526:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
